Bronislaw Krzyzewski Papers 1915-1962 (Bulk 1918-1921) CPAA 07-12
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Bronislaw Krzyzewski Papers
1915-1962
Bronislaw Krzyzewski
CPAA 07-12
1 box (0.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Collection consists of personal papers of Mr. Bronislaw Krzyzewski, a World War I veteran of the Polish Army under General Jozef Haller in France and later in Poland.
Biographical Note
Mr. Bronislaw Krzyzewski was born in town of Suwalki in northeastern Poland in 1896. He came to the United States on May 21, 1914. Four years later on February 25, 1918 he volunteered together with other Poles and Polish Americans to join the Polish Army, which was being formed in France under General Jozef Haller. Mr. Krzyzewski left for France in March of 1918. World War I ended in November 1918. However, he did not return to the US but, together with the Haller's Army left for Poland in April of 1919 to fight for Poland's independence. At this time, he visited his home town of Suwalki. Mr. Krzyzewski came back to the US on January 28, 1921. For his participation in the WWI in the Haller's Army he received a medal. Mr. Krzyzewski lived in Willimantic, Connecticut most of his life and he died there in November of 1977.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of personal notes and photographs of Mr. Bronislaw Krzyzewski. Personal notes include dates of his travel during WWI and text of polish religious and patriotic songs. Collection also includes some family information and handwritten notes on family members.
The collection is open for research.
Related Material
For related material on World War I and the General Haller's Army see: Urbanski, Michael T. "Money, war, and recruiting an army: the activities of Connecticut Polonia during World War I." Connecticut History, 46 no. 1 ( 2007): 45-69.
Donated by Mrs. Camille Chmura daughter of Mr. Krzyzewski in November 2007.
Search Terms
Krzyzewski, Bronislaw; World War, 1914-1918 -- Poland.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Regimental histories -- France.; Poland -- Armed Forces -- History -- World War, 1914-1918.; Polish Americans -- History.; Memoirs.; Photographs.; Uniform.
- Memoir in Polish with raw English translation, kept by Mr. Krzyzewski during WWI in Poland., 1918-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Medal given to Mr. Krzyzewski for his participation in WWI with Haller's Army; he received the medal in 1921., January 31, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Two (2) photographs of Mr. Krzyzewski during his hospital stay in Rowne, Wolyn province, taken Sep. 2, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Prayer book in Polish with a hand written notes: "This book was purchased in Suwalki in 1919"; "Souvenir from Suwalki after 6 years of absence in this town." (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 5 postcards from Suwalki: 4 postcards from 1915 and 1 from 1920 with Russian army equipment., 1915, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- German and Russian currency., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Post card from relative in Poland; obituary of Michal Mazierz, brother in law with additional family info. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Polish post card to Woodrow Wilson with a poem in honor of President Wilson and his role in Poland's independence., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Leather wallet, traveling pouch from Bremen, Germany to the US., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 15 stamps from Poland., after 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Clippings on Poland., September 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Map of Poland, printed by Polish Daily Zgoda., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Jozef Pilsudski" by Seweryn Romin, Paris., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Haller's Army hat from WWI., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bronislaw Krzyzewski papers - material separated. (Box 1, Folder 15)